going to switch gears
to the complications of
myocardial infarction or
acute coronary syndromes
our patient was treated
with PCI back to the patient
with PCI and a drug eluting
stent was placed in the
left circumflex artery after
one week patient was discharged
from the hospital and
returned to his home on
dual antiplatelet therapy.
If we put a stent in
someone, usually also we
end up putting them on
something called the
clobidegril in addition
to the aspirin. So that's
what they mean with dual
antiplatelet therapy.
Two months post discharge,
the patient returns to
the ED complaining of chest
pain that worsens with
inspiration and improves
with leaning forward.
On physical exam, a
substernal friction rub
is heard. On auscultation,
labs show leukocytosis
and elevated ESR and
C-reactive protein.
On ECG, there is diffuse ST
elevation in all the leads.
Lungs are clear to
auscultation bilateral
and there are no signs
of pitting edema.
What is the most
likely etiology
of this patient presentation?
Keep the case in
mind and we're going
to go circle back
and discuss the case.
But let's first talk about
post-MI complication. And
we're going to talk about
them in terms of time frame.
So within the first
24 hours, usually
arrhythmia are the most
common complications.
The most serious ones
are the ventricular
arrhythmia, which include
ventricular tachycardia,
you know, see,
monomorphic VTAC, Or
ventricular fibrillation,
which is multiple
different shapes of QRS,
bizarre QRS complexes.
And that means the ventricle is
quivering because of
the acute ischemia.
So this ventricular
arrhythmia, most commonly
early, most common early
post-MI complication.
It doesn't exclude the
fact that the occurrence
of arrhythmia become
less and less with the
advantage of PCI and
immediate revascularization.
You know, as we know,
the injured myocardium
becomes, you know, unstable
and hyper excitable,
and there are re-entry
circuits that correspond to
this arrhythmia, or can
cause this arrhythmia.
and it's diagnosed by ECG yeah
gonna continue with the
time frame between one
to three days something
called early pericarditis
usually happen in the
first three days early
post MI and it's a
fibrinous pericarditis
and usually it's likely
due to inflammation
You know, as you
started in pathology,
you know,
the pathologic stages
of MI and how the
inflammatory cells are
recruited as a result
of that patient can
have pericarditis.
um clinically it presented
with something called the
pleuritic chest pain which
hurt when you breathe in
and out you can hear something
called the friction rub
on the exam on the
physical exam and
which is like about
to and fro sound like
like something rubbing
rubbing sound and usually self
-limited and usually the
treatment of choice is if
you have to treat it and
patient didn't feel better
you have to treat it with
answers non-steroidal anti
-inflammatory drugs if needed
we're gonna move through
the time frame within three
to five days you can have
a lot of mechanical
complications and this include
papillary muscle rupture and
interventricular septum rupture
papillary muscle
rupture usually
affected the posterior
medial muscle more
and it happened in cases of
right coronary
artery infarction
right coronary artery
infarction you know if it's
occluded um usually um
that's the most common uh
scenario um that can rupture
the papillary muscle um
leads to something called
acute mitral regurgitation
and as a result of
that you may hear a new
hollow systolic murmur, and
it can also be accompanied
with pulmonary edina.
Interventricular
septal rupture, too,
usually happen in left
anterior descending infarct,
left anterior descending
infarct, and usually
lead to left to right shunt.
And as a result of left
to right shunt, there
is high oxygenation or
high oxygen content step
up in the right ventricle.
And it's characterized by
harsh systolic murmur and
usually diagnosed by
echocardiogram with Doppler.
Moving through the time
frame, day 5 to 14,
ventricular
pseudoaneurysm can happen,
and more serious
catastrophic one
called ventricular
free wall rupture.
Ventricular pseudoaneurysm
happens, it's
considered contained
myocardial rupture, contained
myocardial rupture,
you know, myocardium.
contain the myocardial
rupture risk of rupture
remains high within
this time frame and
it can lead to a
pulsatile mass sorry can
lead to a pulsatile
mass with a narrow neck
it's called pseudoaneurase
still contained
ventricular free wall
rupture is more catastrophic
complication which can
lead to complete rupture
and this can lead to
accumulation of blood
around the heart and
cardiac tamponade and this
happened in elderly
patient, more extensive MI,
which is called anterior
MI, extensive anterior,
because it includes a
big part of the heart
muscle, and patient with
hypertension as well,
and the sudden deaths,
and usually a
pulseless electrical
activity are the end result.
Moving through the
time frame, two weeks
to months, patient can
develop true ventricular
aneurysma due to
scarred myocardium,
you know,
scarred myocardium
because, you know, after
that healing, you
know, it becomes like a
fibrous tissue. It doesn't
have the same contractility
as a normal heart
muscle, which is
indicated by persistent
ST elevation on the ECG.
And finally,
postcardiac injury syndrome
called the Dressler
syndrome, Dressler syndrome,
which is an autoimmune
condition. We consider it
autoimmune pericarditis
because it has also a
pleuritic chest pain,
but associated also
with some constitutional
symptoms like fever,
elevated inflammatory markers
like sedimentation rates,
C-reactive protein,
and is usually treated
with NSAIDs or colchicine.
and here is a summary of the
complication um from the uh
first aid usma step one
and back to our patient our
patient had mi had a pci and
drug eluded stent eluting
stent and was discharged
at home after a week and
then two months down the
road he started to have this
pleuritic chest pain which
worsens with inspiration
and improves with leaning
forward so like similar to
the pericardial pericarditis
pain but on physical exam
there was substandard
friction rub which is okay um
here on auscultation uh
but on further work up with
labs he had leukocytosis
and elevated inflammatory
markers esr and c-reactive
protein and on ekg he was found
to have diffuse st elevation
in all leads of the
ekg and his lungs are clear
to auscultation bilateral
and there are no
signs of beating edema
which, you know, give
you an idea about
no signs of heart failure
or pulmonary edema or
anything like that. So
what is the most likely
etiology of this patient
to achieve complaint?
What do you think?
A thrombus formation
occluding coronary
artery vessel, coronary
artery or a vessel,
arrhythmia,
autoimmune reaction
to the pericardium,
decreased left ventricular
ejection fraction,
neutrophilic
infiltration of the
myocardium. What do you think?
Thrombus formation
occluding coronary vessel.
That sounds like MI.
Usually a patient has more
severe pain, not pleuritic.
maybe radiate to the
left shoulder or the jaw
associated with diaphoresis
stuff like that so it
doesn't look to me like
an mi picture or acute
coronary syndrome picture
so it's not the right answer
arrhythmia um ecg didn't
show any arrhythmia
patient was not also
complaining of any palpitation
or anything like that
so I don't think it's an
arrhythmia autoimmune
reaction to the pericardium
maybe let's see stress
d um decrease lift
ventricular ejection
fraction which corresponding
to heart failure no they
said the lungs are clear
and there is no signs
of pitting edema so it
It doesn't sound like
heart failure picture.
What about in neutrophilic
infiltration of the myocardium?
That sounds like the
pathology of pericarditis,
but this patient
presented two months later
and has leukocytosis,
elevated inflammatory
markers, esrc reactive
protein along with the
pleuritic chest pain so
it sounds to me like more
drissler syndrome autoimmune
reaction to the pericardium
and here we go so the
correct answer is c and
here is again is a summary
of the acute coronary
syndrome um and if you
have any questions uh
please don't hesitate
to email me I am always
available by email I
will be ready to answer
your question um I hope
you enjoyed my lecture
and I wish you the best
of luck and feel free
to give us a feedback
so for future are
improvements. There is
always room for improvement.
I hope you have a wonderful
day and thank you.